so we've been uh having we've had the
great fortune to have
um some beautiful teachings in new york
i think we started
10 years ago 10 years ago
yeah you look nice mommy uh
we started ten years ago i think we did
uh four years we did the
yoga sutra we covered the four chapters
of the yoga sutra
myself and loma christie who is now in a
three-year retreat
and then we did four years of hatha yoga
padipika
which is a beautiful yoga text on the
practical
exercises of yoga and the cleansing
processes of yoga
and then we've done two years of
bhagavad-gita
and we still have one more bhagavad-gita
class to go
that will be in january but i it might
be later than i
said uh
due to the camp the camp that we're
going to has a problem
for the retreat so anyway uh
we'll be doing a i think it's a
week-long course or something
on the bhagavad-gita in january and
we'll complete the bhagavad-gita
uh which are the three great classics of
the yoga tradition and there's like
10 more that we can do for the next 20
years if you are they're
they're not they're beautiful like
um we can do a lot of beautiful
we can go on that for a while uh
i thought i thought though today i
thought it would be really beautiful for
these three days
we have three days together um
you know during the last 10 years of
yoga
talks with you we've we've been
concentrating
a lot on on
ultimate reality using yoga
to understand where the world is coming
from
using your yoga practices physical
practices of the body
to come to a deeper understanding of of
your world
and reality and how how your life occurs
why your life is
why your life is happening the way it's
happening uh
due to your inner body okay so we've
been talking about that a lot
and i sort of felt like
we've spent so much attention and effort
on uh
on understanding ultimate reality and
the way reality works
and then i felt as though it would be
nice
if we turned our attention to the
subject of compassion
or love you know which is not treated
that
much in the text that we've been
covering in in the
yoga sutra there are some mentions
like uh the four infinite thoughts right
might be karuna
and infection so we have that teaching
there but there's not a lot
uh and i and i felt as though it was a
lack
i felt that it would be it would balance
us
if we talked a little more about the
teachings on compassion
and love personally i have this
deep feeling that i don't love people
enough i feel what do you call
i feel like i'm too busy to love people
enough and i feel like
uh i don't feel honestly like i walk
down the street and i love everybody in
new york city you know like
i after all these years of meditating
and practicing i still
a guy drove up next to us on the way
here
uh margie was joining me uh which he's
been doing for 20 years or so and uh
and he was blasting this uh what are you
calling
not worse than hip-hop
rap music and it was really loud and i
like
you know how you give him a look which
is what he wanted right
which is why he played it wrong and then
uh
and i gave this look and then i'm
thinking i'm not loving him so much
you know and i don't know after all
these years i
i have trouble even just down the street
just mindlessly
judging people and thinking i kind of
attracted to this one but i'm not so
attracted to that one and
and i move through my day like that i
don't love everybody
equally and i don't feel this outpouring
of love for every person at me
and um i would like to you know
are you warm are you too warm by the way
yes it's a little warm
are you okay yeah it's gonna get warmer
can somebody check the air and crank it
up
i like it freezing because then people
stay awake okay
can somebody check the air yeah okay
just ask them if it's cranked up wrong
way
then people complain later that it's too
cold um
so i honestly i don't feel like that you
know i to be honest
i don't like go down the street and i i
feel
an outpouring of love from my heart for
every single person i see
you know it's it's very uh what do you
call it
prejudice i see someone who looks
attracted to me and i'm like
you know smiling to them and then i see
somebody who's sort of irritated
and but sometimes i do you know there
are days when i
i i don't know about you but there are
days of
deep i don't know short periods
of a few minutes maybe a feeling of
great contentment and a feeling of great
at being at with peace at the world and
feeling like i love everybody in the
whole room and i feel
a brotherly feeling towards them like a
i would call it a a very
current feeling towards them i had it
once on a plane you know the story most
people know the story
i won't tell it very long i'll tell the
short version okay i was on a plane
when i was idaho
i was 18 and we were flying to chicago
and uh it was a normal flight to chicago
and then when we got to chicago the
plane circled for a while and we were
just all talking
and and you know the normal and then the
plane
started to fly out and then down
shocked me and then the pilot would take
the plane up
and then drop a couple hundred feet like
straight down and then he would come out
of the turn
and and jar the plane you know we're all
like whoa
you know the first time it happens you
think it's just the wind or something
you know
but he was like four or five times he
did this you know and then we're getting
we're starting to feel strange you know
and
and then the the stewardess comes out of
the
captain you know the cabin in the front
and she's shaking
she's visibly shaken you know and then
we're like oh my gosh
and then the captain comes on the
intercom and he says
we have a problem you know and we're all
like oh boy
and the plane gets really quiet you know
and then he says
it was really foggy and he says uh
we can't confirm that the landing gear
are down we can't
we can't the light on the in the cockpit
says it's not down
and we can't get it down you know and we
tried to shake it loose
and we think it might be down but we
can't tell for sure you know so
we're going to take a few passes by the
control tower and see if anyone can see
if the landing gear is done
you know so then we're waiting and then
he zooms down close to the ground
really close and zooms past the control
tower you know and we do this a couple
times and we're like
and then and then he gets up in the air
and he starts circling again and he says
nobody can see us and it's too far to
fly to another airport you know like
we can't no one can see if the landing
gear is done and the light's not coming
on to say it's down
so we're just gonna circle until the
fuel
is almost out because if we land and if
we crash land then
it's better for you if there's not much
fuel in the plane
you know so we have to wait for like
half an hour 45 minutes
until the fuel runs out and he's
circling chicago
you know and the plane gets really quiet
you know
and then uh the stewardess gets on
and one stewardess had a breakdown once
they're to start to cry
and they had to take her in the pot and
that's like freaking everybody up you
know
and then then the other stewardess is
walking around saying okay
take off your shoes uh because you can
run faster
all right everyone has to take this any
high heels
anything take your shoes off and then
she goes through real
we're getting really nervous you know
and then she says take off your jewelry
because it will burn through your
fingers you know the heat of the metal
will bring to your fingers
oh man you know people are
writing notes to their loved ones i mean
come on
where are you gonna put the note you
know
and everybody knows it's stuffing it
everywhere you know
and then uh suddenly someone starts to
cry
and then somebody got up out of their
seat and they went and hugged them you
know
and then uh another person started
crying and then another person got up
and started they just went over the
heartbeat
all these people on the plane they just
it's a whole shift around the plane and
then
people are hugging other people and and
saying i don't know you but i love you
you know
it's really beautiful it was really
extraordinary
the whole plate of people were like
hugging each other and
holding each other and just touching
each other it was so
moving and so beautiful and we were just
there you know
and then um at the end they said
put your head down between your knees
you know
and that was the worst part because you
have to you can't see anything
you know and they said put your head
down between these and everybody was
holding hands you know i mean just
spontaneously everybody in the plane is
holding hands here
rolling down like this and they come
down
and come down and hit the runway
everything's fine and uh
there was foam all down the runway and
there was a
long line of fire trucks
on one side and there were ambulances on
the other side
and a lot of hearses and they were just
waiting for us
to crash you know and um so we all like
oh and it was so beautiful
i've never felt anything like that ever
you know and then we got
to the game and everybody it's like i
gotta
catch
and uh it means weird i don't but i
don't think
i often haven't felt that feeling since
then
you know it was just that one special
time and everybody in the plane had this
deep
what do you call it was a spontaneous
love for each other
and that that i imagine must be the real
human condition
and i think the rest must be uh
just nerves or something you know i
imagine that the real
human condition is this deep love for
each other and i would like to have it
all the time
you see i've always wanted it all the
time you know i wanted to be able to
walk around new york and
or at least occasionally a few times a
day to have this feeling towards
everyone else in new york you know to
feel like that towards them
and so what i thought we could talk
about
was uh in the buddhist tradition there's
a state of mind called bodhichitta
means the enlightenment right like
buddha comes from
same root means your mind
and uh some people are translated
enlightenment mind it doesn't mean that
it's a wrong translation it means the
wish to become enlightened okay
uh because you love other people okay so
out of concern
uh for others welfare you wish to become
an enlightened being who can serve them
right it's a love it's the ultimate kind
of love it's the kind of love
that we were talking about uh in the
play right
it's the playing airplane love between
people
and then buddhism goes into long
long long many many trainings
how to develop that kind of love there
are many scriptures
and there are many techniques of
meditation for how to develop that kind
of love and i would like to
i would i personally would like to
feel that what i felt on the plane i
would like to feel it all the time
right it would be beautiful it would be
then life would be something special
you know so i there are many uh
scriptures
and many meditations you can do
um
and then there are there are tantric
practices for reaching the same
state of love okay and they involve the
inner body
they involve the chakras and the
channels
and prana and and they go at it from a
different angle you see
you go at it from the inner body you you
try to develop
love the airplane love for others
uh through physical practices uh such as
awesomeness or kriyas or
or practice with a partner and you try
uh to find you try to open the channels
and the chakras in such a way that you
come to a deep state of love
that way okay and those are two
uh very different traditions you see
one is you could call open teachings
in which you try to develop
love for others through meditation and
through
empathy through your own experiences
that you felt and then the other one is
where you go at it through the inner
body
and you try purposely to move prana
through the inner body
which could trigger a state of love or
compassion
so what i thought would be fun right
what i thought would be interesting
would be to for three days
for three evenings talks to to alternate
between the two
i thought it would be really interesting
to to sit together
go through uh one
one of the great meditations that are
meant to develop that kind of love for
people
and then intersperse it uh
with with the the practices of the prana
and the chakras which are meant to bring
on the same kind of love
you see so you would have a what do you
call i always see it like a military
attack like a pincher
a pincher what do you call it
maneuvering you know
two-prong maneuver you know so over here
you would be
uh doing meditations to try to bring on
a state of love
and then over here you would be working
in the inner body with special
uh practices that are meant to move the
prana
in your body and i thought um it would
be beautiful to try
to go at it from both angles you see in
the same
time for three evenings and then my hope
is that
uh that in the three evenings you would
be left
with a practice of meditation and the
practice of asana
or practice of the physical body the
inner body
that you could use both of them and and
we could try to develop this kind of
love
you know uh and that's a
that's a tradition uh it's called chin
on top lator
we'll talk more about it but um
so what i'd like to do is go at it from
both sides all right
and i just thought it would be really
really nice and then
if if after three days we had a practice
that we could do
regularly and and personally i like to
understand the practice
you see so that means we'll go deeply
through the meditations
we will go through many ancient sources
for those meditations
and for the chakra work i mean we'll go
through
the a very detailed explanation of the
of what happens inside your body
with the prana and the chakras what
happens as you reach
a state of deep love what's happening to
your prana
and what's going on with your chakras
and can you
can you sort of what do you call it
force it can you make it come
faster and and there are beautiful
beautiful teachings on that
uh in the in the text on the inner body
so what i'd like to do is uh
go very detailed into the two
presentations okay one is uh
a meditative presentation and then the
other is an inner body
presentation and and what i want to do
is bring you to that
experience there's a peak experience
of of love there's a very
unique experience of love in meditation
which is triggered by work with your
chakras and if you can
reach it then your life will change
forever your life will never be the same
and you will never be the same person it
doesn't take very long it's five minutes
maybe
it's like five minutes in a meditation
and if you can induce it in a person's
soul right then that person changes
forever
and you you will never ever be the same
and you can never
ever not feel a deep love for other
people
there's a very very profound experience
that you can
bring on with the right training and
and what i'd like to do is see how many
people we can get there
you know and it doesn't take more than a
few minutes
i don't imagine frankly that you can do
it in three days but i think we can
start you on the practices and then you
can
have that experience and that after that
happens to you there's nothing else
that you need okay if there's nothing
else that
that you lack it changes you forever it
changes how you act it changes how you
speak
it changes everything about you and you
you will always be
in love with other people okay and it's
a beautiful
thing to be there you know so i
i want to try to induce that
it's like inducing labor i feel like you
know could we speed it up
and uh not you okay you have to wait
but uh could we
could we precipitate the process could a
few people in the room reach that
experience and it's extraordinary we'll
talk about the experience all right
so i'm going to first start with uh
how this experience is described
in in a sutra okay so sutra in
in in buddhism sutra can have two
meanings sutra can mean
a teaching by the buddha you know like
heart scripture or diamond color sutra
or it can mean hangar
that's a prana okay
there's a one of the meanings of sutra
though is as opposed to tantra
so the word sutra can mean uh
teaching love in a in an open way which
which you could teach publicly and you
could teach to people who are not
interested in the inner body okay and
that would be a suture presentation
so i thought we could start with a
suture presentation
on on how you develop love
for other people how would you develop
this love for everything other people
and if you can reach that love
your life is just happy all the time
okay you're deeply happy all the time
and and you feel inspired
easily to work for other people
tirelessly you don't need
much rest and you just
feel deeply inspired to serve other
people which is a very beautiful place
to be
okay you just want to make other people
happy and you spend all your time doing
that
and it's a very beautiful life it's a
it's a good life uh if you can sort of
overcome your selfishness and reach a
real concern for others
and i think more importantly if you have
something to offer other people
you see i mean like you can love other
people
and you can wish them well but if you
don't have anything to offer them then
they will just
get old and die and you know if
if your love could could take
manifestation
in in some kind of gift that you could
give to people
that would save their life literally
uh take them beyond death then then that
that would be a love you see you could
be in love with everybody and have
nothing to offer them
but you could also be in love with
everybody in heaven and have ultimate
things to offer them ultimate happiness
and deathlessness and uh
it would be nice to have the second
right it would be nice to be like the
second
and you can and you will okay and i
i just want to over the course of three
evenings
to see if i can give you a feeling of
that and how nice it would be
and try to help you get there okay so
here we go
to begin with an open teaching a sutra
teaching
on on developing compassion uh there was
a
sutra that i read many years ago i think
it was uh
how long it was over
it was about 30 years ago and
i was reading the sutra i was teaching a
class and the sister was mentioned and i
went and got the situation and i
and i read the sutra and it was so
beautiful and it
it told a story about love okay and i
thought i would tell you this story this
is a typical
open teaching about developing love and
the buddha it's called karma say karma
karma means karna
means bang means to break or to fracture
bhagav comes from that and v bhanga
means
to present all the divisions of karma
in tibetan it's called mecca namje j
meaning to divide
so like namjang means i will teach you
about the different forms of karma lord
buddha
gave a talk called the teaching on the
different forms of karma this is getting
serious about the air conditioning and
what did they say
they said it was all the way out and
they couldn't do anything else
okay all right turn down the tumor okay
uh so
the suture is called karma vivanga which
means the different forms of karma the
different types of karma
and there's a story in that sutra and i
trans i got it out
i you have to thank the state of arizona
department of motor vehicles
that they have cut the staff so much
that i could
find and translate most of the citra
during my stay there
a couple days ago i'm not kidding
but i found the suture again and uh i
i was number 629 jane
and there were two ladies there anyway
uh
so in this suture lord buddha is
describing to the monks he's talking to
his monks about karma he says i want to
teach you something about karma
okay so he said and i translated and i
put in the reading for you okay
because i love this story it's one of
the most beautiful stories in buddhism
that i've read so lord buddha says
there was a time many many human
lifetimes ago he says bhakti-nepa it
means billions of lifetimes ago okay
there was a time
and there was a young man
his name in tibetan is what's that
which is the ancient vedic rituals of
sacrificing okay uh so his name was
maitrey yajna and uh
he was the son of a of a captain
okay and his father had gone to see this
is in india right
his father had gone to sea many times he
had visited
ceylon sri lanka and he had gone to
indonesia we went recently to jakarta
and to
yogyakarta in indonesia it's a it's a
long journey and it's a hard journey
even just on the plane
okay he went by ship from india it takes
about
in the old days 13 14 months on a ship
okay and those ships were like rafts
they're just
open rafts with little sticks on them
you know and so he he traveled the
father went
and he died at sea he first he
had many successful trips and he came
home with lots of money and
things to style and then finally he died
at sea as his son was growing up the son
had many friends and they were
talking in the sashing which means
uh a park
like park of a fruit trees and they
would sit around there
and they all said look uh our town is a
town of
seafarers and it's weird for us young
people not to go to sea
you know just because your father died
doesn't mean we can't go to sea
you know we can see the world and we can
make our fortune
you know like our fathers dip and we
want you to lead us he they asked
maitri yajna would you lead us
and we'll go to sea and you know we'll
have adventures and we'll get rich and
we'll come home
you know and he said okay i like it you
know so he went home
and he uh told his mother i'm i'm gonna
go to see
you know and she's like your father went
to sleep he died
and you were the only person i had left
i asked you not to go
okay and she says we have lots of money
from father
we don't need money there's no reason to
go okay and you're all i have and i ask
you not to i'm asking you as your mother
not to go
and and he says uh i'll obey your wishes
he wasn't american he was indian
and he said i will i will obey your
wishes
you know and then time went on they had
another meeting in the park
and probably they facebooked a lot and
um
and then his friend said really let's go
okay and then he went home again
and asked his mother he told his mother
i really have to go
and she said no and he respected her
wishes the third
time she
uh she grabbed his she knelt
at his feet and she clasped his
legs and she begged him not to go and
then
uh he he agreed not to go and the fourth
time
he agreed not to go fifth time his
friend said we're leaving okay
if you don't come we're leaving you know
then he went harmony
he told us his mom had locked up all his
stuff in her cabinet
he went home and broke up in the cabinet
he got all his stuff out
and he uh he packed it up in a pack and
he
he went to the door and his mother was
there and she again she grabbed him by
the leg and she knelt down and she
begged him not to go
and he pushed her with his foot and he
accidentally he kicked her head
okay kicked on the head and then she
fell back and he ran
and he went down to the he went down to
the sea and got into a ship with his
friends and they left
you know and then uh
on the way to indonesia they they ran
into a typhoon
and the ship sank and everyone
drowned except for my two yesterday
and then he grabbed on to some
bottles like metal bottles that were in
the ship and he tied them together and
he
he just hung on and then the currents
just carried him
and he spent days uh floating on the
currents
and then he came to a an island he
landed on a beach
you know and he he stepped out of the
water and he looks up
and there's this city it looks like what
do you call it disneyland in l.a
you know except all the walls are made
of gold pure gold
and the city all the turrets of the city
and
all the buildings are made of pure gold
you know and he's looking at the city
and he's
he he gets out of the water and he
he walks across the sand and then the
gates of the
city open and four goddesses four
beautiful
goddesses come out of the city
and they take him by the hand and they
say come with us you know
and uh he goes into the golden city and
they say he spent
uh several hundred thousand years there
with these goddesses enjoying himself
okay the word into banister it means
i almost translated it to sport but it
doesn't sound the same
it means to have a really good time okay
to play it means to play uh like lolita
in sanskrit he means to play and he
played with them
for for hundreds of thousands of years
he didn't get old
and he he lived with these ladies and he
played with them
and then one day they said to him you
know you can't really stay
this is not really your place and then
if it should come that you ever lose
your way
and you you lose you can't get back to
the city you should go north
just go north okay they gave him this
advice one day he was outside the gates
of the city and he got
what do you call him disoriented
and he wandered to a forest and then he
couldn't get back to the city
so he kept walking and walking and
walking and he found uh
he came across another city but the
walls were made of silver
pure silver and uh
same story except it was eight goddesses
uh came out of the walls and took him
inside and they played for
they stayed thousands of years and he
enjoyed the pleasures
of their company for thousands of years
then same thing happened they said
if you if you lose the city then you
should go north so he did one day he got
lost in the woods
and he traveled north he came to a city
of
lapis pure lapis lazuli and then same
story but it was 16
goddesses and then the next city was
32 and oh i forgot to say an important
thing
before they went to see standing at the
dock
he suggested to all his friends we
should take vows
you know we should take one devos okay
it's called
uh donbaget
it's called the eighth the eighth house
it's an eight
vowels of a one-day vowel no no killing
no stealing
no sexual misconduct no lying no alcohol
like this no sitting on high seats no
luxury
like this they took a they took a vow of
of mindfulness for for a one day
right and uh so then he came to a city
of crystal
and the same thing except how many
goddesses 30
sorry that was 32 4 8 16 then 32
okay uh then one day he left that city
and he got lost but this time he entered
a forest of
thorns a forest of thorn bushes
very difficult to get through the thorns
and
then he came to this city and the walls
are made of iron black
iron and he wandered through the gates
he stepped inside the gates
and then the gates slammed behind him
like this
and then he hears this screaming he
hears this person screaming at the top
of their lungs you know
and he's like what is this place and he
looks up on the
on the top of the parapet of the wall
and there's a man standing there
okay and
he's screaming he's just screaming and
he says
what's wrong you know and the man comes
down the stairs and then he can see uh
there's a crown an iron crown on his
head
right and inside the crown there are
these little
razor blades like uh wheels
and knives and they are chopping away at
his head
they are the knives in the crown
are are chopping away at
the flesh of his head and cutting open
his head
and and they just keep going and he
can't get it off he tries to help him
get it off and they can't get it off
it won't come off and he's and he's he's
like
what is this thing and he said i what
what did you do how did this come by the
way those of you
studied what lojong the wheel of shark
weapons this is the crown
this is the real crown it's not some
wheel of shark weapons it's a crown of
of small knives cutting away this head
and you can't get it off you know and he
said how
how did you come to this place and how
did this crown come to your hand
you know and and what do you eat how did
how do you live here and he says i've
been here thousands of years
i've been here many thousands of years
you know he said so how do you survive
he says
blood comes down my face and i drink it
and i haven't died
you know and then he says well what did
you do that this crown came on your head
you know what was the karma that you did
for this crown to come on your head he
said i was
a young man i lived in a city near the
sea
my father was a ship captain but he died
at sea
and and i always wanted to go to sea
and my friends and i talked about it
many times
and i decided to go and i talked to my
mother and i asked her permission and
she said no and i obeyed her for four
times
and then on the last day i kicked her
head by accident
running from the house and i went to sea
and the ship sank and i swam
and i came to this land and i walked
across the face of the land
and first i saw a golden city and four
goddesses came out
you know and jampa children he's like
and then the guy keeps telling him then
i spent
a long time in the golden city and then
i was in the silver then i came here
and i walked in and the door shut behind
me and there was a man
standing on the parapet screaming and he
had this thing on his head you know
and he came down the steps and he told
me his story and then the crown came off
his head
through the air and came to my head
and then
he said he told the man i've done the
same thing
i've done exactly the same thing you
know the man said i
i think so because i heard a voice today
and it said your tile is finished
the time of the crown is finished
another one comes
to take the crown you know you know
so um i just know he's saying oh my
you know he's like seeing the pain that
the man is
in and he he gets very very frightened
and and the man drops dead
and the crown goes into the air you know
and then he's
it moves towards him and then he's very
frightened and he
but he closes his eyes and he prays for
his mother
you know he just makes a prayer
for his mother you know he says in my
last you know moments here
i pray for my i pray for the
my mother and that she should be happy
and then something breaks
open in his heart something breaks open
and he says you know may the crown come
on my head
and may all the pain of the world come
through the crown to me
you know i will take the
pain of the entire world through the
crowd let the crown come
now to my head and
and i choose to take not only that pain
but i choose to take the pain of every
living creature
in this world human or animal all their
pain
let it come now through the crown to me
he chooses to accept the pain
and he he prays that the pain
of all people and creatures would come
to him
through the crown and he waits for the
crown to fall
and then because of his prayer the crown
cannot come down
okay the fair cannot come down and the
crown stays
here you know and it never touches his
his flesh he never touches him so he
stays there many years the crown
is following you around and he can't
touch him
it cannot come down because he had that
one moment
you see of real love you know he had the
one
moment of wishing that he could take on
the pain
of people and then lord buddha finishes
the story he says um
he says don't think that was someone
else okay
don't think that boy was someone else
that was me that was me
in a in a former life that was myself
and that's and i that's how i found love
you know it was through a very terrible
tragedy that i found love
you know that's how i found love and
so that's the sutra
in the scriptures this is how love is
often found through a tragedy
okay and
when when we are training in bodhichitta
when we are
trying to learn how to become a
bodhisattva then um
in the scriptures they say if you're
lucky you have a tragedy in your life
okay your mother dies in your arms
my brother killed himself and uh
if you're lucky something like that
happens and then you
in the depths of true
tragedy and sadness somehow
it opens your heart and you're able to
love other people
because you have some deep tragedy in
your own life
because something really bad happens to
you
then something opens in your in your
heart and you're able to notice that
other people are suffering
you know other people have the same
thing whatever tragedy you have
other people have that tragedy and many
many other tragedies
life is tragic for everyone
there's no one who's protected from
from those tragedies that happen to
everybody if you haven't had one yet you
will
okay they come and and life is
uh they define many people's lives the
the deaths that have occurred around
them or
or the accidents that have happened to
them or to their friends
and change their lives forever
our lives are defined by these tragedies
and then
many of us cannot open our hearts until
a tragedy comes
it takes uh some great
pain or suffering to notice what other
people are going through all the time
okay so they say if you're lucky
you have a tragedy and then you step
first upon the path
so the path has five
stages all spiritual evolution occurs in
five stages
and in at the level of a bodhisattva on
a bodhisattvas trap
you enter the first stage to a tragedy
and you see what life is and
death and suffering of a life and that
puts you
on the path it starts you on the path
you see that's the open teaching
okay that's the traditional
presentation of how you first get love
for other people it's through a tragedy
in your own life
and then you're able because your heart
is open you're able to see what's
happening to other people
okay so that's the
open teaching what i'd like to do next
i'd like to take a break
and then what i'd like to do is i'll
give you the tantric version
okay the inner body version of the same
experience you see
like related to chakras and to the prana
within your body
and and let you let us work from the
inside
and from the outside from both in both
directions
okay so i'll take a break i'll be here
i'll stay here if you
want to say hi if you have a personal
question
um you can or you just want to say hi
you can come talk
try to try to be sensitive that there
are other people who also would like to
talk
okay and if you don't get
through the line in the first night
don't get all worried okay because i'll
be here a couple other nights and i'll
stay late the last night
okay unless they kick me out and you'll
you'll get there so don't be all
stressed okay
and just come and talk um maybe we'll
take a 10-15 minute
break and then we'll come back uh
and we'll continue on the inner body
way to open the heart okay
and then uh i'll give you a little bit
we'll start on the inner body
uh methods for developing
love and then i would like to
open the floor for questions if you have
any questions
the questions don't have to be relevant
or very good
okay you can ask about you can ask about
anything you want i
i think uh ask about what's on your mind
okay
what's on your own mind and especially
if you're
if you're having some problem or you're
struggling with something yourself
and i think that helps everybody in the
room you see
if someone is uh very honest about
something that's challenging them at
this moment
and they ask about it then it helps
everybody in the room
okay so don't be shy and don't feel
weird it doesn't have to be relevant to
what i'm teaching okay
uh just ask about what's on your mind
right now
and something you need help with and
then i think it will help everybody
all right so we'll do first we'll have a
short meditation
then i'll talk a little bit about inner
body
and love and then we'll go into some
questions okay ready so get ready for
meditation
so i'd like to introduce you to the text
the root text that we're studying
okay
say uh
means a song of spring
and children's are very common in in
tibetan
scripture sanskrit scripture china means
a song of springtime
because the heart chakra
inside the hot chakra the very core of
the heart chakra
is a tiny drop which is known as
it means uh the drop of spring okay the
drop of springtime
why it's called that and what it does
we'll be talking about
because it's important for the
development of of that airplane love
okay so this is a song about
that part of the body
in this stream i'd like you to go to
page one
and uh just as a blessing we started
event with me okay you ready
somewhere mommy
so this is the first of the eight verses
of this song
it was written by a monk named sanchez
okay uh
so llama means your heart teacher okay
sorry lama the first words mean heart
teacher
uh means by their
kindness something happens at the
at the heart chakra okay something
happens at the heart chakra
so now we're the second half of the
class
we're going to talk about the tantric or
the yogic
view of what's happening inside your
inner body when you when you
feel like you want to cry for love of
other people you see
like uh on the plane or something like
that
okay when you have an experience like
that what's happening inside your
your heart chakra in
in terms of the inner body how would you
reach
the same place as the young man
who is willing to take on the pain of
the world you see
how would you reach the same place
uh in terms of the inner body okay and
for this you need to know
a thing called uh panchamarga say
panchamata
the word finger comes from pancha okay
because there's five of them i mean on
one hand
and marga means five
packs and these are five
uh steps five steps in everyone's
spiritual evolution no matter who you
are
no matter what tradition you follow
sooner or later
you will go through five different steps
in your spiritual evolution
all right from what from a human being
to a
being of light okay there are five
steps that everyone goes through in that
process okay
and these are called the five paths or
the five
stages okay you can go through those
stages on three levels
uh the lower two levels in the lower two
levels you are going through the five
stages
because you don't want to have suffering
yourself you want to free your own self
from suffering
in the higher charge of those five
stages
this is what we call the bodhisattva
okay and you are
your goal is to protect the world the
whole world from suffering not just
yourself
okay so i'm going to describe
how a bodhisattva goes through the five
stages all right
and and you have to remember that it
means a person
who wants to help the world a person who
doesn't want the world to suffer
right and they're part of the world okay
don't forget that right the bodhisattva
themself is always one of the people
they are saving okay
it's not like you say everybody else and
you forget about yourself
you do everybody at the same time okay
so here we go
uh we talked about the first path
the first of the five paths the first
stage of every person's spiritual
evolution
is a tragedy of some kind okay they
become aware of the pain of the world
somehow in some way they become aware of
the pain of the world
and they take a true concern in the pain
of the world all right
and everybody has their own story people
tell me terrible stories about how they
first discovered pain and
it seems like the worse the story the
better the student
okay so or the more committed they are
right okay so if you have a terrible
story be happy
okay uh second level
second pun
in the pursuit of trying to stop the
pain in the world
you gain some great insight into how the
world works
right in in your pursuit
of bringing happiness to the entire
world you have some
very great breakthrough uh understanding
how the world works
okay basically meaning that the world is
coming from how you treat
other people but we'll talk about it in
more detail okay you have a breakthrough
in seeing how you could modify the world
because the world is flowing from your
own mind you have a
a deep understanding comes to you of how
the world is flowing from your own mind
this happens to everybody sooner or
later it happens to everybody and that's
the second of the five paths okay
the third path is probably the most
crucial it's called tongan
tong needs to see lam means a path
and sometimes it's called the path of
thing uh
because you have been working on trying
to understand where the world is coming
from
uh you meditate deeply you practice
deeply
and then in deep meditation tongue can
only be
the first part i told i'm only a person
in deep meditation
you must be in deep meditation and you
will
have a direct insight into reality okay
you will have a direct perception or
you can say a communion with ultimate
reality
okay and it's it doesn't take more than
20 minutes or something
it's 20 minutes of time it occurs in
deep meditation
it takes billions of lifetimes to get
there okay
you are lucky you are in uh
good times you can do it in this life
you are at the last
life uh of billions of lifetimes
in tibet they say you are the bullet
brushing the target
you know you are the bullet the metal
front of the bullet is brushing the
paper of the target and the ball is
about to pass through
uh the target you are there you have a
time you have chance
you have the teachings you can do it in
this lifetime
but you have a in deep meditation you
have a
direct communion with a higher reality
if you have that communion if it happens
to you
you will become enlightened within a
short time okay what's a short time
let's say 500 years or something okay no
compared to trillions of years
countless years okay you are very close
okay
uh if you have that experience
then it it you become unstoppable
okay that experience does something to
your
mind and you you can't be stopped you
will become an enlightened being
within a short time very very short time
okay if you can reach that
only my llama has the number
okay
so during that time that you have that
20 minute experience you are
in such a deep meditation that you can't
hear anything
you can't see anything you cannot be
aware of the passage of time
and you cannot even be aware of yourself
okay
during that 20-minute experience the
meditation is so strong and so deep
uh that you cannot be aware of any other
thing
uh only ultimate reality which is
completely different from this reality
okay you cannot be aware of any part of
this reality
during that 20 minutes
and that's not even talking about what
you're seeing you see what i mean
the the meditation is so strong that if
somebody
put mcdonald's french fries in front of
your nose you wouldn't smell anything
okay that's pretty deep all right
and then you go into a direct uh
perception of ultimate reality inside
the body
inside the chakras something
extraordinary is happening at that time
you see
mentally in the meditation uh
unusual things are happening you are
having a perception
which can create a perfect world within
a few lifetimes
okay something is happening in your mind
but in parallel to that something is
happening in your
chakras and in your inner body and it's
very very
uh unique okay uh
and we'll talk more about it and you've
had
a lot of those teachings basically you
have a
chat you have a channel running from
this point
uh below the skull runs under the skull
comes out uh in front of your
spine at the base of the neck and then
travels down
the body they say very close to the
front of the spine
and then comes down to the groin and
then and then there are
side channels that split off there are
other towns of plot but mainly you have
one
and it runs from here down to the groin
normally the channels inside your body
carry prana
the channels inside of your body carry a
special energy called prana
uh but prana cannot travel through the
central channel now in in if you have a
human body
of flesh and blood it's proof that your
central channel is not open
okay all right if you have this body
now it has formed around
a central channel which was blocked okay
and which was choked
and that creates the the build build-up
of this stuff called
flesh okay you get a buildup of called
what's called flesh and that's your body
that's your gross body
so because the
central channel is not open because the
prana cannot flow through the central
channel
the body itself forms in the womb okay
and you
and you take on a mortal body a body
which will die a body which is doomed to
die
a body which must die okay left
untreated by
yogic practice the body must die okay
if you know how to practice properly the
body doesn't have to die
but that's because you will open the
central channel okay normally
in in most people the central channel
doesn't open
for the passage of prana except for two
times in their lifetime
okay you you know all this we've done
this for ten years
uh during uh death
okay as you die the central channel
opens briefly
okay the the knots that choke
uh the central channel open briefly
during the experience of death
when the urine is released and feces is
released then
blood will flow from the nose and then
all the inner
knots are opened okay not by any yogic
practice
uh just by the nature of karma okay when
you die
uh all of your chakras loosen
and your central chin in your central
channel prana flows for the first time
and then the winds the downward wind and
the upward winds are released
to flow freely and and you you you
you do your last act which is to pee and
to poop
and blood flows from your nose and you
die the consciousness passes
okay also in the act of sex okay
in during uh during a full
orgasm uh for a few seconds
the central channel is opened okay and
and prana flows through the central
channel very very briefly
uh then there's an ejaculation or
release of fluid
and then the nature of karma at that
point is that they close
up tighter than before okay and you feel
exhausted or you feel
you don't feel well really it's a it's a
release
of prana briefly and then there's a
reaction
the the knots uh tighten again
and uh you don't feel
you don't feel that way an hour later
you see what i mean
during the actual orgasm your central
channel is open and
the prana is briefly flowing and then it
shuts again
okay
and that's because especially knots
that are tied around the channel the
central channel open
okay during so only in those two times
of life
is your central channel open and
if you're able to see if you're able to
go into the direct perception of
ultimate reality
then the channel opens okay the central
channel opens
it in that deep meditation and in that
deep perception of where
all things come from and the direct
communion with
with a with a higher
i think it's what people probably
thought was god
who may have been in in a tradition like
christianity or judaism and they had
this experience they would think it was
god
okay it's a direct communion with that
with that
higher reality okay
and uh and then your central channel
opens wide open and you have this
experience you see
so the purpose of yoga
in buddhism in tantra is to bring on
that experience
the whole purpose of asana in
in buddhism uh is to open the central
channel
to get the knots out of the central
channel and to open it
and then you will have this experience
of ultimate reality so we
we work on uh on the various poses of
asana which we'll talk more about
tomorrow there are special
series of poses and progress
progressions of poses
that would facilitate the opening of the
chakras
so that you would have the direct
perception of of ultimate reality okay
so i'm now on the third path right
and we just had our first direct
perception of ultimate reality
maybe 20 minutes and it's an unstoppable
force that
will within a relatively short time
make out of you an enlightened angel
with the power to stand
on billions of planets at the same
moment and serve billions of living
beings at the same moment it's cool
okay it's really cool this body is a
mistake
this body is crap that built up this is
uh
i have mineral in my water in arizona
okay
and i have a drip system for the garden
and uh
every year i have to throw all the
pieces into vinegar
because minerals deposit uh on all the
holes
and the sprinklers won't work minerals
build up
your body has built up on your channels
like that
the flesh of your body has built up
like mineral deposits on on a sprinkler
you know and then when you open the
channels that dissolves
uh it's like vinegar okay and then your
flesh
changes and you and you go to where your
body was supposed to be which is light
okay this is not the natural condition
of the body this is
dude this flash will get wrinkled and
old
you know there's a joke in buddhism if
you spend two hours in the yoga class
you're two hours closer to your death
when you get out
you know it's not that it made you
younger
okay so
seeing ultimate reality will change the
body
then something happens in the hours
following
your first communion with ultimate
reality okay
something happens in the hours following
that experience you see
you basically go back to the same way
you were before
you cannot maintain that perception it's
not possible you don't have the karma
it's not nobody can maintain it more
than 20 30 minutes the first time it's
not possible
it takes a tremendous amount of karma
to see ultimate reality directly nobody
can sustain that
perception for more than a half hour
it's not possible the first time
so you've used dr karma and then you
come out
of the direct perception of ultimate
reality and then you're back in the
world of mcdonald's french fries
and you know the room that you're
sitting in
and your own body and michael
you come back into michael you see
because michael wasn't there either
michael was gone for that time because
michael's not ultimately
reality okay you come back
to your body to yourself to your mind
you remember what happened but you can't
see it anymore
all right it's not possible you can't
sustain it
okay but something cool happens okay
this is not a tantric level
inside your central channel hasn't
closed back all the way yet
okay it was opened completely
your heart your heart chakra was opened
completely
but it does it's not like the moment you
come out of the meditation
it just closes again it stays open for a
couple
it stays open until you fall asleep the
same day you can call it
about 12 hours or
8 to 12 hours the channel is still open
okay
and cool stuff happens because when the
channel is open your whole mind is freed
okay you can see the future
you look you can see into the you can
see the day of your own enlightenment
and you can see what you will look like
in that moment okay
you can read other people's minds
clearly exactly what they're thinking
you can hear it in your own mind okay
like you can go to a used car
salesman and
let's say you had this happen to you and
you wanted to make an offer
to your mama it's okay and you you said
i'll sell my car
because that's all the money you have
right and then you go
take your car and you tell the guy i
need money
right now and i'll take whatever money
you have whatever you want to give me
i'll take then you can hear the person's
mind
clearly directly you can hear haha
this little guy is a fool you know this
is going to be good
i can make some money on this guy you
know and then they
you you're talking to them verbally
but you're hearing the thoughts behind
in their mind while they're talking and
it's
it's very uh amazing and it's very
dis what do you call it dismayed
to really hear a person's thought as
they're talking to you
you know to hear both at the same time
that
the dissonance between the two is quite
uh
disturbing okay uh
so for the hours following the direct
perception of
ultimate reality the central channel is
still
open it's in the act of closing it's
it's closing it as you
and and then when you fall asleep at
nine it has closed
okay the whole thing is and it's over
and it may take you
lifetimes to come back to that
experience okay it's a very
uh unique experience but something else
cool
happens during that time all right
during those hours
in tibetan say jaito yeshi
the aftermath of seeing reality
in the hours following that experience
when you came down
out of that experience your heart chakra
is still open
your heart chakra is still slightly open
okay
and then you can have this experience of
ultimate love you see
what i'm trying to describe i've tried
to lead you
to another way of having the experience
of ultimate love
that the buddha described about the son
of the captain
you can get to this love a different way
you can travel a different path to the
same sort of love
and it's much much more beautiful
and it's extraordinary your heart chuck
if you can open
your heart chakra briefly
then there's this intense uh
feeling of colorless
water colorless uh liquid
uh bursting out of your heart like a
geyser i tried to find a picture of it i
googled for like an hour i give up
uh that that picture is the closest i
could come
okay but don't but don't imagine it
coming down
imagine it coming this way out of your
heart
okay imagine that colorless
uh we call it
it's like a bar of colorless water like
from a hydrant that's flowing really
hard so it's like a bar of colorless
light
it's light which has no color and it
bursts
out of your heart chakra so that's what
it feels like it feels like it's
bursting out of the front of your chest
like a colorless light
and i believe that's where they got the
name clear light
but it's i think the word is a little
insufficient
it's a colorless light that's the point
it's a light which has no color
and you feel it and you can see it
bursting out of your chest
okay then you have this intense
experience
where uh
let's say you're on a let's say you're
passing a bus
in your car right and you look up at the
bus and you're passing the bus in the
taxi
and then you see the faces of the people
one by one right
so as the car is passing the bus we're
assuming the bus is slower than the cap
and and you look up and the people are
looking down at you in the cab
and you see one face in one row and then
you see that person in the next row and
then you see the piece
the face of the person in next door one
by one right so you see maybe 10 faces
out the window of the camp now try to
imagine something
that you could see all 10 faces at the
same time
distinctly in the same place
okay shorten the time and you perceive
ten faces in the same place at the same
moment
okay try to imagine that that you saw
the ten
faces of the people on the bus but it
didn't happen one after another
it all happened at the same time okay
you saw all 10 faces at the same time
right in front of you okay got it
multiply that times all the faces of all
the people in this world
six billion faces at the same moment
okay throw in all the creatures who are
not human
okay from amoebas to fish
to insects to birds throw in the faces
of every other kind of living thing in
this world
you are watching this many faces
at the same time in the same moment
because your heart chakra is open
when the heart checkers open you have
this capacity the
natural capacity of a human being
is to be able to see billions upon
billions of faces
of the living creatures on this planet
at the same time
that is your natural state
your present limitation only to be able
to see one face on the bus after the
other that's a
that's a mistake that's not your natural
condition
okay you are blocked from your natural
having a body which is mortal and which
is aging
is is not your natural condition you are
blocked
because of the knots in your channels
okay
now multiply that times all the worlds
on which
there are living beings okay try to
imagine
in a single moment
looking upon the face not of every
living creature
in this world but all the worlds there
are
like multiply that times an infinite
number of worlds
okay you are watching at the same moment
an infinite number of faces on an
infinite number of worlds
because your heart chakra's open and you
are back to your normal condition
you are back to your natural condition
this is your natural condition
you have the capacity now add the
airplane love to them
okay you're looking on the face
of every living being in every world
and in the same moment you love them
like the people on the airplane okay you
have intense
love and concern for them like the
people on the airplane try to imagine
loving infinite beings
as you watch them in the way you would
look your lover in the face or something
you see that
you have one lover right and you can
look at them in the face and you can
feel
a certain emotion towards them multiply
it times
the number of faces there are in the
whole universe
and you have that capacity and that's
love
that's a real love uh
but you see how we got to it by
different means you see
the young man waiting for the crown to
come down on his head he's having some
kind of a
emotion where he's wishing
that everybody he's imagining everybody
in the world
and he's thinking i love them and i want
to take their pain
the young man standing waiting for the
crown of nice
to come down on his head is imagining
all the people in the world and loving
them and wanting to take their pain
now imagine a different person they are
sitting on a meditation cushion
they have just seen ultimate reality
directly and now they're in this direct
perception
of the faces of every living creature in
every world where there is life among
countless billions of planets and they
are loving them all at the same time
directly and and that's love
that's real love and and if that
experience happened to you
what would you be after that how would
you act the next day
what would you be like the next day if
it happened to you once and you knew it
was for real what would hap
how would you feel the next day
i don't know it would be nice
i mean trying to imagine just try to
imagine if you had that experience once
and if you knew you weren't like crazy
if you knew it was real
no i mean you'd have to know right by
the way you do have another
they call it a confirmation perception
you you realize you're not crazy okay
uh there's another perception which
confirms the first perception
okay uh try to imagine how you would be
after that
try to imagine how you would be if you
had looked in the face of every living
thing and loved them
unlike the person you must love in this
life
okay you try to imagine
how you would feel about yourself i am
capable
of loving billions upon billions of
beings
in the way i love the person i love the
most in this life
at the same time and see them all
at the same i have this capacity then
there comes another very beautiful
perception okay
one more then i'll stop then you can ask
questions huh
there happens another perception you see
in the future the day that you will
become a being
who can take care of all of them at the
same time okay
so to be an enlightened being
means that you have the capacity
to take care of countless people at the
same time
you are able to split your body avatar i
love that movie
you know i love the idea i love the word
avatar
okay you will be
you will have countless avatars you will
stand
in countless worlds you will stand next
to countless beings
you will have the capacity without
conscious thought they say
say london sundered means without
conscious thought
without any intention to do so
you are suddenly reflected you are
splintered
into billions of creatures on billions
of planets to serve each person okay you
have this capacity you see it
directly you see how you will be
they know what else you need i mean what
else do you need in your life you see
if you have seen that if you have had
that experience
what what why would you worry about your
rent
or you know what i mean or or the last
boyfriend you had
or you know or traffic
or how how would you be after that try
to imagine how you would be after that
and you'd be really happy okay because
you would have
seen the purpose of your life and you
would have seen how your life is going
to
turn out there's not much suspense after
that
okay but you you have this capacity okay
so the practices we are going to
undertake
the practices we're going to discuss in
the next two days
are all aimed at getting you to that
experience okay they are
we're just gonna talk about different
ways
of getting you to that experience
because once you've had it
then your life is like i can't describe
it you have to try to imagine what it
feels like
you have to try to imagine how would
your life be after that
how would you feel towards other people
and
and the whole worry about dying or
what's going to happen to me
or you know what's going to happen to me
next year what's going to happen to me
after i die or why am i here or
what am i supposed to be doing or you
you you would be the only person
among thousands who knew why they were
here and what they were supposed to be
doing
and they you wouldn't know your future
and
and how would you act then what would
your life be like after that and i
i suspect that's happiness okay that's
love and that's happiness you would have
love
for every other living creature and you
would be happy
you would be deeply deeply healthy
because there's nothing more fun than to
take care of
one other person and then you would have
a direct perception of yourself taking
care of billions of people
at the same time and it just
there wouldn't be any higher kind of
happiness you would be
you'd be happy for the rest of your life
deeply happy okay
the karma of that experience is that you
will never not have a heart teacher
the karma of that experience the seed
planted by that experience
is that you yourself will always be
taken care of by
by a perfect teacher but by a perfect
heart teacher okay the karma
of that experience is that you will
never ever be without a heart teacher
they will always be with you and
wherever you go
dead die don't die wherever you pass
you because of the few minutes
of intention and perception of yourself
helping countless beings you you earn a
heart teacher
who will always be close okay and
and nothing can change it nothing can
can separate you after that it's not
possible
okay so it's pretty cool right
and uh you have to my goal and what i
would like to try is
we'll do some more meditations we'll try
to get
uh try to induce labor
and uh and see if we can induce the
experience
you know uh from and outer
practices and from inner practices okay
and that's what i
that's my that's what i really want to
do
if we can do it okay maybe we can do it
in three days maybe take longer maybe we
do some more later i don't know
but let's start with let's start with
that okay you know what the goal is now
okay you can have that experience it
will come
okay all right uh we have like 15
minutes if you have any
questions they don't have to be about
this you know you can ask me about your
boyfriend uh
okay if you have any
oh i'm sorry i gotta tell you one more
thing because it's on your homework okay
so there is homework uh there is a
certificate for this course
uh it
it uh authorizes you to induce labor
in people and you'll have to do
homework tomorrow and the next day uh i
think there's a homework in your
folder and what i'd like to ask
is that you uh i like to ask that you
should do your homework with somebody
else and
cheat nicely together okay so
i if it's possible for you logistically
uh i would encourage you to do your
homework with someone else there will be
people here tomorrow out in the little
living room right
right am i right tas teaching
yeah we're gonna have study groups
tomorrow at 7 15. and if your last name
starts with
a to l stephanie johnson raise your
hands
you're gonna hang out with stephanie and
she and this is optional she can help
you out with your homework and if it's
m through z michael hewitt raise your
hand you're gonna hang out with michael
here and he's gonna help you out
here yeah from 7 15. then the class
starts at 8.
but if you would rather what i like to
ask people is that
if you can approach
someone else in the class whom you don't
know
okay whom you have never met even as we
leave tonight
i i'm requesting uh that you approach
somebody that you don't know
and say would you like to do the
homework together tomorrow
sometime it could be here it could be in
a coffee shop it could be anywhere okay
so i'm asking everybody even if you've
come here for 10 years
i'm asking you there's probably like six
people who haven't been here before
they're going to get all these
people approaching them uh
just approach somebody don't be shy and
just say you know
i normally would never do this but
michael said i'm supposed to and would
you like to do
uh homework tomorrow together and then
do it together
okay i have to cover the there's three
long questions okay the third question i
didn't cover yet
okay i'll cover it for like five minutes
then we'll have 10 minutes of
questions um
do you think these two approaches
for developing ultimate love can be
reconciled
do you think there's some i'll tell you
the two approaches again okay
one is the traditional sutra approach
you see
that approach is that you have a tragedy
in your life
you have a crown of stars of knives
dropping down on your head in about
three minutes you know what i mean and
then you are
pushed into the experience of love or
you're on an
airplane and it's gonna crash and then
suddenly everybody in the
something happens to the hearts of
everybody in the plane and you are all
forced into this kind of relationship
with each other
okay a sort of a intense love for each
other
due to some kind of tragedy or disaster
okay that's the sutra approach
or the tantra approach or the approach
we talked about as far as the inner body
your heart chakra just opened for other
purposes
and then it's still open and then you
have this perception of
of all the living creatures and you have
this intense love for
all of them can those two approaches be
reconciled
do they meet somewhere what do you think
are they the same or are they different
it's two different ways
the same experience two different ways
to the same experience
anybody else
through the first yeah the tragedy would
be to the three principle paths
and you would develop enunciations and
which would
set you up for voting cheetah and
correct you
and then through the process of those
analytical
investigations of method and wisdom you
would lead yourself and it would break
down your door
yeah so she said basically that you
would have
intellectual understandings of of what
we call renunciation love and
and the direct assertion of emptiness
right and then
and then you would be able to break down
the doors that separate you from others
like that through that intellectual
process anybody else
is there one common force which is which
is creating both experiences
okay okay try to appreciate that okay
the reason the young man
had those thoughts as the crown was
coming down
was the karma of his love for his mother
okay the reason he was capable of of
of coming to a deeper love in that
moment of
of of terror was
was karma you see he had
he just finished the prayer for his
mother do you remember read the text
okay you have the translation
read the thing when you go home okay i
feel so bad i i go to somebody's house
the thing is covered with dust that's
okay
i say did you ever read it they say no
you know that hurts
okay so uh so read it on the way home
it's not very long
he makes this intense prayer for his
mother's happiness
and then that triggers all this other
higher kind of love
he has created the karma he has created
the seeds
in his mind for this breakthrough how
about the
other person what makes the prana moved
through the heart chakra why does the
heart chakra open
it's karma it's just karma okay
you can do all the asanas you want you
can do twists until you are
twisted forever uh
and it won't open your heart chakra you
see the prana won't come through the
heart chakra
the reason it comes to the heart chakra
is because you've you've done some great
kindness to other people okay
then you go to yoga and it opens it you
see what i mean
the kindness created the yoga class the
kindness created the truth
the karma of being kind to others
created the
asana which opened your heart chakra you
see what i mean so
you can say that the two great
methods presented tonight they meet each
other
in the sense of karma okay you you be
kind enough to others often enough and
you will
and you can have either experience or
both experiences okay
that's what causes them that's what
makes prana flow
in the end it's it's always your
kindness to others
which makes the pronoun flow okay all
right any questions
we have like 5 10 minutes
yeah nobody else
right after the boy makes the prayer
for the sake of every living being it
goes to at the same time his mother was
making her own
oh yeah and
she sends she says she says
you know son be released i love a little
love and then
then it says and then so the crown
denies his appearance so i wonder
yeah why is that passage there
okay uh mercedes is asking about a
passage
which if you read the selection from the
sutra
after the young man completes prayers
for all living beings
and the crown is coming down towards his
head
it says his mother back home was making
prayers for him
his mother back home was dedicating all
the karma of her life
you know all the good deeds she'd ever
done she was
taking that karma and she was offering
it away to her son
wherever he might have gone like she
didn't know if he was dead or alive
and she was trying to send her karma to
that boy and then the text says
and then the wheel stopped due to
implying that it
happened because of these two things
right
and it's a good point because in our in
our tradition
we say that you cannot give karma to
another being you see that
you cannot do a good deed the mother
cannot be a good mother and then send
the boy the karma
by fedex you know like uh we say that's
not possible
okay you cannot share uh your good
comments with other people you can't
give away your karmic seeds it's not
possible
what's the proof it's not possible
my car broke down last week twice
okay in the same week okay aside from
being a financial disaster it was uh
it was scary i mean the second time it
broke down on the highway going like 70
miles an hour and it started bucking
you know and i just barely got off the
highway
so uh if it were possible
for any enlightened being to take away
someone else's seeds
at will i would not have had my car
break last week
got it the presence of any undesirable
thing in your life
is itself proof that it's not possible
for enlightened beings to take away
their seeds because they would have
already
and you wouldn't have had the problem
you don't need to be able to see
enlightened beings
you don't need to be able to confirm
everything philosophically
the fact that you got your teeth drilled
by the last dentist you ran into
is proof that no one can take away your
cease no really it's just
it's self-proof and there's no other
proof needed okay
you can't take away someone else's seeds
and you cannot give someone your good
cover
why the text thinks that maybe you can
talk about it in your
homework groups i have no idea
there's a reason i mean the buddha says
things for a reason
the buddha always says something for a
reason now why
i wondered myself when i translated it i
thought
we should talk about it maybe tomorrow
we'll ask if anyone came up with
a good idea okay all right i think we
have time for maybe one or two more
questions
natural and this is so unnatural
why does it take so long and so much to
get to the natural state of things
yeah good she said if if being
if our being a being of light is our
natural condition and having a body of
mortal flesh and blood is an unnatural
condition
why did it take so long to get out of
the unnatural condition
to go to the natural condition did you
ever try to
scrub mineral deposits off of the
sprinkler i mean it's like
crazy i don't know if no it takes hours
and hours you
soak it in vinegar and then you heat it
and then you weigh and then you struggle
against it
why it is i would say uh
maybe the build-up has been taking so
long you see
the build-up of flush has gone on for so
long we say
this is not the first build-up of flesh
you've had
you've had it countless times you've had
it billions upon billions of times so
maybe that's what makes it so hard to
reverse
right good question
she said what made it why did it start
to build up in the first place
okay uh
the the build-up of flesh
results from negative emotions
ultimately okay ultimately also cancer
tumors
even in this life a lot of it is
emotional
you know and it and then flesh builds up
you have a body of flesh and blood
because you have anger
then you're supposed to ask me why do i
have anger
and then the answer is because you had a
body of flesh and blood before that
and then you're supposed to say well
where did i get that one and then i have
to say anger
and then you get frustrated and you say
well when was the first party
which is to say which came first the
chicken or the egg and then a buddhist
has to say
there have always been eggs and chickens
you have there's no beginning to the
lifetimes you have left
you have had this kind of body
to have this kind of body requires
before it a state of anger
to have that anger requires a body
before that
there's no beginning okay
it's
no and then you come out you come out of
it we are in a temporary condition
and there are many worlds in which all
the people have already changed
and we are like the my teacher said i
can't say retards anymore
we're like the challenged people
like we're like the last people left in
the whole
universe that didn't get it you know and
really this is a temporary setback okay
this world
where people are killing each other and
people are hungry
and there's war and there's fighting
among us
the people sitting here you know we
can't get along with each other
this is all temporary very very
temporary it's not our natural condition
this is a small step back in the
grand scale of things it's not our
natural condition
we won't stay like this we're almost out
okay one more question i think anybody
mama can believe um well it relates to
the natural condition so
love is our natural condition she's
feeling into the logic of this say the
natural condition of our mind is it the
inseparability of them
to love together as our ultimate
condition as our natural condition that
brings love in as our natural condition
yeah
i was thinking about it today because uh
we had an earlier program
uh at the three jewels and uh
we were studying a text on
which is uh a very very secret practice
about
eliminating stuff okay and um
part of the meditation for chu involves
recognizing that all beings have been
your mother
right like you have been
you have ripped apart the guts of
everybody in this room
okay in the past in your past lives
you have you have
struggled your way out of the womb of
every person here male or female
okay you have been born
with great pain out of every person here
in this room okay you you have killed
them
in childbirth countless times you know
uh and they have given you life at the
cost of their life
countless times so in the practice of
should you think about that
and you try to develop a kind of uh what
do you call gratitude
for the people around you you know you
see them you say you know right now you
look like the person who grabbed the
last chocolate chip cookie before i did
but i know in fact that you were my
mother in my past life
and you lost your life for me and i
appreciate it you know
and you're supposed to think like that
which always struck me as odd because
they has also murdered you countless
times
you see that you've all murdered each
other countless times
why then i'm always waiting for somebody
to ask me this question you know like
well why don't i just think about how
badly they murdered me countless times
then i can abuse them at will you know
everybody i meet has been my
has murdered me i should get them back
yeah
and uh you have to come up and then
answer
which is the following um
love is our natural condition okay and
it is the true condition
and hatred is an unnatural condition i
in in china they call
tao right
uh in in daoist idea which is beautiful
dao means the natural condition of
things the natural flow of things
okay and to love other people
is natural and to hurt them and to
dislike them is unnatural okay to hurt
other people is unnatural
and against the doubt against the flow
of life
and to love them is in accordance with
the flow of life
why
because they are not separate from you
okay they are not separate from
and then you say that's ridiculous she's
sitting over there i'm sitting over here
you know she got a chocolate chip cookie
during the break i had to talk to people
you know we're not the same you know
that's
not true we're gonna go home now
to different houses probably and
we're not the same we don't have the
same address you know we're not the same
but then this system
you cannot get any good thing in your
life
it's not possible to get anything you
want in your life
good unless you provide it to someone
else
first it's not possible okay i cannot
have anything good
chocolate chip cookie for example okay
i cannot it's not possible for me to get
a chocolate chip cookie
in this yoga center tonight
unless i give one to someone else before
that
unless i have offered one to someone
else before that it's not possible
you cannot get a nice car unless you
give other people rides
you cannot have a nice house unless you
are concerned about sheltering other
living beings you can't have the things
you want
without providing them to others first
it's not possible
because those things are flowing from
seeds in your mind
which are planted from being kind in the
same way to somebody else
you cannot have anything you want unless
you provide it to someone else first got
it
so what's the difference between them
and you if i cannot have a chocolate
chip
cookie enter my mouth unless i assure
that a chocolate chip
cookie enters your mouth first what's
the difference really between the two
mouths
you see they're in different locations
they're connected to different hands but
and i'm not debating that but ultimately
i cannot get a chocolate chip cookie
unless i put one in your mouth
first then what's the difference between
your mouth and my mouth your mouth
becomes my mouth
functionally i need your mom
no i'm interested in talking to kurdish
it's one of my main
practices and
i want them i like them
and uh actually i don't but i'm just
kidding so don't bring me talking
but i therefore i must assure that they
enter the mouths of other people and
then what's the difference between their
mouth and my mouth
because really their mouth is a conduit
to my own mouth get it yes
so really i in the natural flow of
things
love is is the natural condition and
hatred is not
hatred it is against the tao he to say i
am separate from you and you can suffer
and i don't have to suffer
this is against the thumb this is not
the nature
of things the nature of things is that
anything you want you must share and
when you share you become the other
person
so love is the natural condition it is
to not it is our natural condition
to to take care of each other because
you can't take care of yourself without
taking care of other people
okay and the opposite is not our natural
condition
because it just hurts us it's against
life to
to do things which damage yourself see
what i mean
which is not sharing
cool so you should you should
concentrate on how everybody has
borne you from their womb and you
shouldn't worry about the all the times
they killed you
okay okay that's my answer to myself you
see because the one is the natural
way we are and the other is not okay got
it
okay we're going to do a short prayer to
dedicate the good camera
get some sleep okay the next two nights
are gonna go late they start at eight
so that the yoga here the yoga teachers
here we don't want to hurt their income
so we won't have class until they're
done with their classes here so we'll
start at eight
uh we'll go till 11. uh so be ready to
put out
don't be wimpy okay you're gonna save
the world you can spend an extra hour
okay and uh thank you for coming
and it's uh i love new york it's an
honor to be here
and i love to have uh i love all of the
faces the people
here i know you most of you and uh
and it's very precious time that we
spent and i look forward to it and
uh and this is a beautiful thing to talk
about and
it's a beautiful life to live to have
people
to have friends like you and that we can
sit together and talk about these
beautiful things
okay i'm very uh happy
and grateful okay all right uh who's
gonna do this
really wait
i'll embarrass you okay
yes
okay thank you